Lula Pace collection, Inclusive: 1895-1969, undated, Bulk: 1899-1907
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Lula Pace collection
Inclusive: 1895-1969, undated, Bulk: 1899-1907
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
508
Pace, Lula, 1868 - 1925
5 document boxes and 1 oversized box
The Lula Pace collection contains student notebooks and topographical maps owned by Lula Pace, a graduate of the University of Chicago who went on to serve as a science professor at Baylor University.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Lula Pace was born toWilliam Jennings and Olive Wilder Pace in Newton, Mississippi, on 1868 November 3. Within a year, the Pace family relocated to the Central Texas region, settling in Bell County.
One of the advantages to this new residence for Lula Pace was the presence of Baylor Female College in Belton. Pace earned a Bachelor of Science degree from Baylor Female College in 1890. For the next few years, Pace taught in Temple’s public schools. During the summers, she attended the University of Chicago. This hard work, which continued over nine consecutive summers, paid off for Pace. She graduated from the University of Chicago with her Master of Science degree in 1902. Shortly thereafter, she became an Assistant Professor of Biology at Baylor University. In 1903, she was the only female professor in the science department and one of only five at the entire university.
Pace flourished in her position at Baylor. She continued her education during the summers and graduated with her Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1907. Her dissertation concerned plant cytology. The degree earned Pace the honor of becoming the first female professor at Baylor to ever hold a Ph.D.
From 1903 to 1925, Dr. Pace continued to teach courses in biology, geology, and botany. In 1907, after earning her Ph.D., Pace was appointed the Chair of the Department of Botany and Geology at Baylor, a position that she held until her death.
Dr. Pace was popular among her students for her professionalism and her field trips which she led across Central Texas, the Rocky Mountains, and even as far as Yellowstone National Park. In 1910-1911, Dr. Pace took a sabbatical to study under prominent German botanists at the University of Bonn. She came under attack from conservative fundamentalists, including Dr. Frank Norris of Waco, for teaching evolution as part of her curriculum, but was supported by many Waco citizens and Baylor President Samuel Palmer Brooks.
Pace passed away at the age of 56 on 1925 June 16. She was survived by her mother, a sister Mrs. A.C. Buchanon, and a brother R.E. Pace. Rev. J.M. Dawson and Dr. Samuel Palmer Brooks officiated.
Scope and Content
The Lula Pace collection materials range in chronology from 1895 until 1969, with the bulk of the materials dated from 1899 to 1907. There are two folders of correspondence written to or concerning Dr. Pace. Most of the literary productions are Pace's notebooks that she completed as a graduate student at the University of Chicago. Series II. Literary Productions also contains some of the lab reports and articles that Pace published, including a geological survey of McLennan County. The third series consists of topographical maps from Illinois, Indiana, and Wisconsin. These materials are presumably from her geology classes at the University of Chicago.
Arrangement
Prior to this latest round of processing, the Lula Pace collection was housed in two document boxes. The inventories provided accurate folder listings of these materials, but the collection lacked any series. The folders were also over-stuffed. The name of this collection has been changed to the Lula Pace Collection to reflect the manner in which the materials were gathered from various sources. Notebooks that were originally stored at a rate of 2-3 per folder have been re-foldered with only one notebook per folder. Most of the titles have been kept.
The collection is now organized into three series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, and III. Maps. Series II. Literary Productions is by far the largest in the collection.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 508. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Lisa Asher. “A Brisk Pace: A Professor Who Set High Standards in Class and Far Afield.” Accessed 2013 February 20.
Baylor Round-Up. 1906.
Lula Pace collection, Accession #508, Box #1, Folder #14, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
"Pace, Lula." Vertical File. The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
"Transfusions Fail to Save Life of Baylor Professor." Waco News-Tribune, 1925 June 17. Accessed 2020 April 28.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Pace, Lula.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; University of Chicago.
Subjects
Baylor University -- Faculty.
Genres
Articles.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1906-1969, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains two folders of correspondence. The first folder consists of letters written by acquaintances of Lula Pace. For the most part, these are reflections of Pace's character. The second folder contains two letters written to Dr. Pace. The materials are in good condition.
  - Concerning Lula Pace, 1928-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Lula Pace, 1906, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Literary Productions, 1900-1949, undated; 2
  This series is the largest in the collection and contains the literary productions produced by Dr. Lula Pace. Notebooks and assignments from her time as a graduate student make up most of the series. There are also some publications written by Dr. Pace, including a "Geology of McLennan County, Texas." The materials are in average to good condition.
  Arrangement
  This series is organized alphabetically according to the type of material.
  - Article: The Botanical Gazette: “Apogamy in Atamosco”: Lula Pace, 1913 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Article: The Botanical Gazette: “Fertilization in Cypripedium”: Lula Pace, 1907 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Article: The Botanical Gazette: “Parnassia and Some Allied Genera”: Lula Pace, 1912 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Article: The Botanical Gazette: “Some Peculiar Fern Prothallia”: Lula Pace, 1910 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article: The Botanical Gazette: “The Gametophytes of Calopogon”: Lula Pace, 1909 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (1 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (2 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (3 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (4 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (5 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Assignment: Chemistry (6 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical Materials: Lula Pace, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: General, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Essay: History: Non-Intercourse Act of 1809, 1901 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lab Reports: Plant Physiology (1 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lab Reports: Plant Physiology (2 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lab Reports: Plant Physiology (3 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lab Reports: Plant Physiology (4 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notebook: Botany: Morphology, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notebook: Botany: Special Morphology of Pteridophytes, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notebook: Botany: Special Morphology of Pteridophytes: Loose Materials, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Continental Evolution, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebook: Cytology, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook: Ecology, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notebook: Ecology: Loose Materials, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notebook: General Geology and Continental Evolution, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebook: General Geology and Continental Evolution: Loose Materials, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebook: General Morphology, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Geographic Geology, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Geology and Botany, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Geology and Botany, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Geology and Botany: Loose Materials, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: History, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: History: Loose Materials, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Map Studies, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Map Studies: Loose Materials, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Petrology, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiography, 1901 summer (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiography: Loose Materials, 1901 summer (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiography, circa 1901 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiography: Loose Materials, circa 1901 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiology: Growth and Movements, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiology: Growth and Movements: Loose Materials, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Physiology and Classification, 1900-1901 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Plant Physics, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Plant Physics and Geographic Geology, circa 1901 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Plant Physiology, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Plant Structure and Classification, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Questions Concerning Geography, 1905-1906 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Literary Productions: Notebook: Thallophytes: Algae and Lichens, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Literary Productions: Note Cards: General, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: Notes: General, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: Periodical: The Baylor Bulletin: “A Few Texas Plants”: Lula Pace, 1922 December (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions: Periodical: The Baylor Bulletin: “Geology of McLennan County, Texas”: Lula Pace, 1921 January (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Plaque, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Maps, 1895-1901; 3
  This series contains eleven topographical maps from the American mid-west. Pace, as a graduate student at the University of Chicago, studied the geology of the surrounding areas. The maps are in average to good condition and have been placed in Mylar sleeves for preservation purposes.
  The materials in this series are arranged alphabetically.
  - Illinois (Box [1063] OVZ, Folder 10)
  - Indiana, 1900 (Box [1063] OVZ, Folder 11)
  - Wisconsin, 1895-1901 (Box [1063] OVZ, Folder 12)